# Hail, gladdening light
# Of His pure glory poured
# Who is th'immortal... #
This is the church that my parents
attended when I was growing up.
Members of my family have been
baptised, married and buried here.
For our services, we drew on the
rich tradition of Anglican hymns
following the biblical exhortation
that we should lift up our hearts
and sing.
In the details of the story of
Western church music are to be found
insights into the human condition
and into our relationship with God.
MUSIC: "Requiem Opus 48"
by Faure
My schooldays were spent
as a chorister here
at St Paul's Cathedral.
The beginning of a lifelong passion
for choral singing.
# ..Dona eis requiem... #
In this series,
with Harry Christophers
and his choir, The Sixteen,
we'd like to take a journey
through the last 150 years,
looking at some
of the great composers who shaped
the world of sacred music.
Over the next four episodes,
I'll be travelling across Europe
from Germany and the music
of Brahms and Bruckner
to the intensely personal voices
of Faure and Poulenc in France.
MUSIC: "Kanon Pokajanen"
by Arvo Part
In Eastern Europe, I'll be looking
at the music of Part and Gorecki
and the role of sacred music
as communism crumbled and
the Iron Curtain was swept away.
In the fourth and final programme,
I will be searching out the links
between music and spirituality
in 21st-century Britain.
But, our story begins in
19th-century Germany and Austria
with the music of Brahms and
Bruckner,
two giant pillars
of the great Germanic tradition
and musical descendants of JS Bach.
They were composers of great
conviction, makers of music
both sacred and secular.
But two men who could not have
been more different.
# Ecce sacerdos, magnus... #
Anton Bruckner, born in the secure
heartland of a declining
Austrian Empire,
was a devout Catholic
all his life and his music is a
confident affirmation of his faith.
And, Johannes Brahms,
a north German Protestant.
He confidently addressed
questions of faith, death,
and human existence.
But, ultimately, found himself
unable to believe in anything
but his music.
# Mit Fried und Freud
ich fahr dahin
# In Gottes Willen... #
By the end of his life, Johannes
Brahms had secured his reputation
as a great composer
and a master of the symphony.
But his early career
was launched by his less well known
sacred choral music.
Work that is deeply personal,
profoundly human,
and distinctly German.
So, I've travelled to his hometown
of Hamburg,
the second largest city in Germany.
In 1833, somewhere around here
in Speckstrasse,
then known as Specksgang, or
Bacon Alley, Johannes was born.
MUSIC: Piano Concerto No. 1 in
D Minor, Op 15, by Johannes Brahms
Johannes' parents were
essentially a respectable
working class couple.
But the area they lived in
was desperately impoverished.
Frankly, a slum.
His father was charming
and good-looking.
He worked as a bugler for the town
militia and as a "bier fiddler" -
a mildly contemptuous term
for someone who plays music in the
streets, and in bars and cafes.
Christiane, his mother, was
17 years older than her husband
and had probably given
up any hope of marriage.
She was, however, a good
cook and housekeeper,
and an excellent seamstress.
Not particularly prepossessing
to look at, she did have
clear, sparkling, blue eyes.
A characteristic
inherited by her son.
By the time he was 13 years old,
Johannes was already
a pretty accomplished pianist.
It seems he was sent
off to play in the Lokale,
bars in the St Pauli district
around here that also served as
cafes, coffee houses, dance halls
and brothels.
Later in life, he would describe
his childhood as a curse.
But he also said
that he didn't regret it.
Perhaps when he played the piano
in the brothels, his fingers moving
automatically,
he was able to dream,
compose, even read.
He was a prodigious reader.
In other words, the experience
may have strengthened him.
MUSIC: "Three Sacred Choruses"
by Johannes Brahms
Here, at St Michael's Church in
Hamburg,
we can locate the roots
of Brahms's spiritual life.
He was born and brought up
a Lutheran, of course, and
he certainly took seriously Luther's
insistence on the importance of a
close personal study of the Bible.
The Bible was a book that Brahms
knew extremely well and he used
as a resource all his life.
Brahms never made any clear
statement about his beliefs,
but seems to have been
a true agnostic,
doubting some of the fundamental
doctrines of Christianity.
Nothing, it was said, made him
angrier
than when it was assumed he was
a conventional believer because
of his religious compositions.
For him, the Bible was a source
of poetry, of morality,
and, perhaps, a source of wisdom.
But not necessarily the word of God.
For the music of Brahms,
Harry and the choir have come to
the Church of St Anne and St Agnes
in the City of London.
It was built by Sir Christopher Wren
after the Great Fire, virtually
destroyed during the Blitz
and rebuilt in the 1960s for the
Lutheran congregation of the city.
MUSIC: "Ein Deutsches Requiem"
Op. 45, Johannes Brahms
It's an appropriate location to
record some excerpts from the key
work of Brahms' early career -
the free-thinking and deeply
humanistic German Requiem.
What's fantastic about
the German Requiem
is the whole story behind it.
His whole personality behind it.
The choice of texts which, for
me, is the most inspiring thing.
They are so personal to him
and his beliefs.
Ladies and gents,
can we have you please?
Brahms, of course, sets his texts
in German,
but because we've decided
to perform some of the extracts
in English translation,
you might lose some of Brahms'
perfect setting
of the German syllables.
But I do think you gain that
immediacy of understanding.
# Blessed they
# Blessed
# Blessed are they that mourn
# For they shall have comfort
# They shall have comfort. #
# Blessed... #
'As part of his research for this
performance of the German Requiem,
'Harry has joined me in Hamburg
for a visit to the Brahms Museum
'and to meet its director,
Joachim Kossmann.'
Hello. Nice to meet you.
Hello. Lovely to meet you.
Welcome
to the Johannes Brahms Museum.
It's not just writing a requiem.
It's taking the sections from the
Bible, which he knew so, so well,
and making something that is very
personal, making his own statement.
And that's what gives the piece
its eternal musical life.
This is a very, very important
document
because this is the handwriting
of eight-year-old Brahms.
That's beautiful.
Isn't it beautiful?
It is a letter to his teacher
saying, "I'm sorry,
"I haven't practised enough
last year but I will practise more
next year."
Because the teacher, Otto Cossel,
was always very critical
about his compositions.
He wanted him to practise piano.
This teacher saw him
becoming a piano virtuoso.
But Brahms had other ideas.
The Requiem is a substantial work,
over an hour long
normally performed with a
huge orchestra and chorus.
Harry has chosen to perform it
in this much less known
four-handed piano version.
This was Brahms' own arrangement
at the request of his publisher.
His publisher thought, in order
to get the work better known,
not only throughout Europe
but also into England, let's make
an arrangement for a piano duet.
We've actually got a Bosendorfer
piano of the same period,
so there's a particular
quality to this Bosendorfer.
It has a thundering bass
and a really eerie top register.
Of course, you lose the colours
of the orchestra.
But what you do benefit from
is that you get the vocal colours
which can get so lost
in a big orchestral version.
# Das Gras ist verdorret
# Und die Blume abgefallen... #
The picture of Brahms that I grew up
with is of an old man with a huge
beard, a huge white beard.
Stout, twinkly but perhaps
a little bit aggressive.
This picture is Brahms in his 30s,
around the time when he wrote
the German Requiem.
He's actually quite a slight
young man.
Although his face is getting
a little bit round.
Very handsome.
Those famous piercing blue eyes.
Above all, this picture,
to me, is a picture of
determination and of confidence.
Look at that tight-set mouth.
I suspect that Brahms never
doubted his own gifts.
I think Brahms knew
that he would make it,
that he had something
important to say.
In the spring of 1868,
the young, unknown composer
had a version of his Requiem
ready for performance. And by his
own admission,
feeling wretched with nerves,
he made the journey
to the cathedral city of Bremen,
100 kilometres west of Hamburg.
Brahms' worries weren't about
technical matters like
under-rehearsal.
I suspect his anxiety had
deeper roots.
The Requiem wasn't written on
commission. It was something Brahms
felt compelled to write
and it is patently a deeply felt
statement of his faith,
whatever that might be.
It was also
potentially controversial.
A requiem performed
in a great cathedral on Good Friday
and absolutely no mention of Christ.
# Ich hoffe auf dich
Ich hoffe auf dich
# Auf dich
# Ich hoffe auf dich
# Der Gerechten Seelen sind
in Gottes Hand... #
150 years after the event,
it's not difficult to imagine
why Brahms chose
to unveil his masterpiece
at the Easter concert in this
beautiful, impressive cathedral.
# ..Der Gerechten Seelen sind
in Gottes Hand
# Und keine Qual ruhret sie an... #
The work is carefully titled
Ein Deutsches Requiem -
A German Requiem.
German in this case referring to
the language sung rather than to
the composer's fellow countrymen.
Brahms said he almost called it
A Human Requiem.
As to Brahms' faith, well,
around the time of the first
performanceof the Requiem,
he wrote his conductor, Rheintaler,
a letter.
In it he said, "I could dispense
with passages like St John, 3.16."
The passage he could dispense with
goes like this.
"God so loved the world that he gave
his only begotten son
"that whoever believes in him
should not perish
but have everlasting life."
Brahms couldn't have made
himself clearer than that.
# How lovely is thy dwelling place
# O lord of Hosts
# Thy dwelling place
# O lord of Hosts... #
Brahms got away with it.
His music was interspersed with
pieces by other composers - Tartini,
Bach, Schumann.
Rheintaler cleverly suggested that
they should also perform Handel's
great aria from the Messiah,
I Know That My Redeemer Liveth.
Brahms didn't object and so Christ
did get a mention after all.
# ..How lovely is thy dwelling place
# O lord of Hosts... #
Over 2,000 people came to listen,
including friends and other
influential musicians.
Brahms, still in his thirties,
had finally arrived.
# ..Yea, fainteth, it longeth,
yea, fainteth, it longeth
# Yea, fainteth, yea, fainteth,
yea, fainteth
# For the courts of the Lord... #
The original idea for the Requiem
must have been closely bound up
with the death of his mother.
The first mention of the peace
is in a letter
written only a few months
after she died,
so she must have been on his mind.
And in the sublime 5th movement,
which was held back from the
performancehere in Bremen,
we find a promise
of maternal comfort.
"Now is your time of sorrow
but I will see you again."
# Ihr habt nun
# Traurigkeit... #
The movement is a
bit of a stand-alone movement.
It's a totally different
atmosphere from the other pieces.
It's very...comforting. I think
that's the main word. Reassuring.
And I was told by a wonderful singing
teacher who said you have to imagine
yourself as an angel,
or possibly once you've had children,
you imagine yourself as a mother
and that's certainly the way I think
about it
when I'm singing this reassuring,
comforting presence
that's going to heal all the wounds
and badness in people's
struggle through life.
# ..Ich will euch wieder sehen
# Und euer Herz soll sich freuen,
freuen
# Und eure Freude soll niemand
von euch nehmen... #
A requiem mass for the dead, missa
pro defunctis,
is normally composed for
the performance at funerals
or memorial services.
The word Requiem comes
from the first line of
the standard Latin text.
"Requiem eternam dona eis, Domine."
Grant them eternal rest, O Lord.
Brahms produced something different.
A concert requiem, or with his
piano version, even a domestic one.
# ..Ich will euch wieder sehen... #
Brahms was only 33,
but death had already cast
its shadow onto his soul.
To uncover what I think is the
earliest and deepest layer of
inspiration for the German Requiem,
we have to turn the clock back
15 years.
Whilst celebrating his 20th birthday
hiking down the Rhine,
Brahms passed through Dusseldorf
and there he had an encounter
that would change his life.
Imagine the young Johannes, who was
on holiday, deciding on the spur of
the moment
to come here to this house
to call on one of his heroes,
the composer Robert Schumann
and his wife Clara, the formidable
piano virtuoso.
He'd never met them before so he
must have been extremely nervous.
He knocked on the door.
And they were both out. However, he
came back the next day, tried again.
And Robert Schumann
answered the door.
This is the first floor
of the house
so it could very well have been
the place where the piano was and
where music was played.
So we can imagine Brahms coming
here, his heart in his mouth,
to meet the great composer
and his formidable wife.
So Brahms sat down and played
one of his own piano pieces.
At the end of the session,
Robert Schumann turned round and
said to the young man, "You and
I understand each other."
The Schumanns were German music's
most celebrated couple.
Always on the lookout for emerging
talent,
they now publicly proclaimed
the unknown composer, scarcely
out of his teens, as a genius.
Brahms, Robert declared,
was the chosen one,
whilst Clara wrote that he had
come as if sent directly from God.
This must have had a huge impact
on Brahms's self confidence
but their friendship was to be
cruelly cut short after only a year,
when Robert Schumann was afflicted
with mental illness.
It was a descent into hell.
He was seized by violent attacks
of hallucinations
and, with tragic irony, he was
tortured by strange, unearthly music
and nightmarish mocking voices.
Finally he could stand it no longer.
One night he ran from his house in
his dressing gown, came to a bridge,
and threw himself into the Rhine.
He didn't kill himself. He was
dragged from the river by some
fishermen
and asked to be taken to an asylum.
Two and a half years later,
the great Romantic composer
Robert Schumann was dead.
His wife Clara and his
young protege, Brahms,
were stricken with grief.
A decade on, Brahms still felt it
as an enduring and agonising loss.
In the 6th movement of the German
Requiem, there's an anger that was
boiling up in him.
Brahms really was crying out to God,
"Why have you taken
Schumann away from us, away from
me and the musical world?"
Brahms just erupts. It's really
incredibly exciting music.
# Der Tod ist verschlungen
in den Sieg
# In den Sieg
# Ist verschlungen,
verschlungen in den Sieg
# Tod, wo ist dein Stachel?
# Tod, Tod, wo ist dein Stachel?
# Holle, wo ist dein Sieg?
# Tod
# Wo ist dein Stachel?
# Holle
# Holle, wo ist dein Sieg?
# Wo
# Wo ist dein Sieg?
Harry, there are so many
interior contemplative moments
in the Requiem.
This is not one of them, is it?
This is hugely, obviously dramatic.
Dramatic, almost angry at times. Yes.
I mean, I feel it suddenly
gets the choir to sing this amazing
legato, rich harmonies going around.
It's almost the opera
he didn't write, it seems.
The choir are now singing at
absolute at full pelt, aren't they?
Yes.
# Holle, wo ist dein Sieg?
# Holle, wo ist dein Sieg? #
They're crashing away. Amazing.
Fabulous, absolutely fabulous.
It's a marvellous bit to sing,
isn't it? This release... It expands.
..you can be expansive.
It's hope, isn't it?
It's a positive device,
isn't it, that lovely ascension?
The whole Requiem is a requiem
of hope.
Out of his personal experiences
and emotions,
his very human anger and grief,
Brahms had produced a masterpiece.
Beautiful choral music with
sincere sentiments that resonated
with audiences and performers
no matter what their faith
or religious beliefs.
After playing through the
four-handed piano arrangement,
Clara Schumann wrote
to the composer,
"This is a truly tremendous work of
art and it moves the entire being
like nothing else before it."
Within five years, the work
had been sung across Germany
and had had performances in Vienna,
Paris and London.
# Blessed, blessed, blessed
# Blessed are the dead
# The dead... #
Brahms's Requiem is one of the most
challenging pieces to sing.
I think you need immense stamina
to get through it.
Not just vocally, but emotionally.
The singers have to find the depth
within themselves and the strength
to cover all the places
Brahms wanted to take you.
When you have a whole performance of
it in one go, I think the audience
is very often shocked
to feel the immensity of emotion.
# From henceforth... #
It's a remarkable achievement.
The Requiem made Brahms'
name and reputation.
And though still a young man,
he now settled into his role
as a major composer.
He moved to Vienna,
the European capital of music.
And while there, he created some
of the 19th century's greatest and
most deeply felt symphonic music.
And it was the symphony
that drew our second composer,
Anton Bruckner, to Vienna as well.
Despite some similarities,
these were two men from very
different spiritual backgrounds.
In contrast to Brahms' upbringing
within the Protestant tradition,
Anton Bruckner was
a devout Roman Catholic.
To explore some of his magnificent
sacred music,
Harry Christopher's choir,
The Sixteen, have chosen to visit
Dowey Abbey,
a monastery in Berkshire.
Here, the abbey church
possesses both the appropriate
devotional atmosphere
and a generous acoustic that allows
Bruckner's unique voice to be heard.
# ..Dona eis, Domine
# Et lux perpetua luceat eis... #
This is Anton Bruckner photographed
shortly before his death in 1896,
when, after a lifetime of obscurity
and failure,
he'd finally been recognised as one
of the great composers of his age.
During his years of struggle, it
was the Church
and the composition of church music
that he turns to time and time again
for consolation.
# In die illa
# Illa tremenda
# Quando coeli movendi... #
The first of 11 children,
Anton was born in Ansfelden,
a village hidden away in a
forgotten part of upper Austria.
The community was conservative,
even reactionary,
untroubled by any new ideas being
hatched in the big world outside.
For a child born here, expectations
cannot have been very great.
# ..Judicare saeculum
# Per ignem.... #
Like so many Austrians of the time,
the Bruckners were pious people.
The most important legacy
of Anton's upbringing
was his unshakeable faith.
Even when, in later life, he may
have had doubts about his music,
he never lost trust in his God
and the Roman Catholic Church.
Anton's father died when
he was only 12 years old.
On the very same day,
his mother brought him here, to
the great monastery of St Florian.
And begged the prior
to take him on as a chorister.
This was an act
not so much of callousness,
as of rigorous good sense.
Despite his age -
Anton was a little too old -
the Prior agreed to take him on.
His mother was not to know
that she'd introduced her son
to the place that was to be,
for the rest of his life,
his spiritual home.
In this beautiful and ancient
establishment of work and prayer,
Bruckner was protected from the
outside world.
First, as a boy chorister,
then, in his twenties,
as the church organist.
He felt he had a calling
to serve God
as a musician
and as a composer of sacred music.
There it is, the organ
that Bruckner played while he
was at the monastery.
It's rather impressive.
Klaus, thank you very much for that.
So, you were playing Bruckner's
organ.
Yes, this is the organ
which inspired Bruckner
for his work, his composing.
It's not the original console.
You can see it's a modern piece
installed in 1951.
But the rest of the organ, the
pipes, would have been what he knew?
Yes. That's right.
The case is original,
with more than 7,300 pipes.
That's a big, big organ.
And his duties would be to play
at every service?
I think he played a lot of services.
He used to, we know, improvise.
Improvising was the speciality
of Anton Bruckner.
We know he did compose few pieces
for the organ because he was a big
improviser.
And a very good improviser.
MUSIC: "Missa Brevis" Sanctus
by Palestrina
# Sanctus, sanctus
# Sanctus... #
In this self-contained world,
the music-making that accompanied
every ritual and service
was traditional and conservative.
For the budding composer Bruckner,
this was a technical education
in Catholic church music at its
most refined, pure and profound.
# Sanctus... #
HARRY CHRISTOPHERS: We know
he loved the music of Palestrina
and other Renaissance composers.
Looked to the way that music
was built, and built on it.
Enlarged it into a whole
succession of masses
which tend to get bigger and bigger.
# Sanctus, sanctus
# Sanctus, sanctus... #
Hello. Hello.
Nice to meet you. It's a pleasure.
This is absolutely beautiful.
Friedrich,
you're one of the librarians in this
extraordinarily beautiful library.
I should put gloves on, shouldn't I?
Yes.
This book is...
This is a copy
of the Missa Solemnis,
composed by Anton Bruckner
here in the monastery.
My reading of German is
non-existent. So that says...
"Missa Solemnis in B.
"Zur hochfeierlichen Infulierung
des hochwurdigsten Herrn Pralaten
Friedrich I."
The Provost was elected in 1854,
and for the feast, Anton Bruckner
composed this Missa Solemnis.
So, this was printed in...
It is handwritten by himself.
By Anton Bruckner.
So, this is by Bruckner?
Yes.
Can I open it further?
Let's see what his script is like.
Oh, wow.
MUSIC: "Missa Solemnis"
by Anton Bruckner
Oh, the labour of
love over all of this.
Just fantastically neat.
This almost obsessive neatness
gave me an insight
into the dogged dedication
that Bruckner brought his calling
as a composer in the service of God.
He'd only just turned 30
and the writing of this solemn Mass
proved to be a turning
point in his development.
It was the last composition he dared
to commit to paper for five years.
Perhaps, realising
he still had much to learn
and that he needed to grow as a
musician, he decided to move on.
When he was offered the post of
organist here at Linz Cathedral,
he was told he looked a little
shabby and might have to
tidy himself up a bit.
His playing was magnificent and, of
course, he was offered the job.
Bruckner hesitated.
He managed to persuade
the monastery to keep his old job
open for two years
and only when he had
that reassurance
would he take up his new post.
Now that he was a fully fledged
professional musician,
the hard work could begin.
Over the next five years,
instead of composing,
he decided to take lessons -
a correspondence course with a
Viennese teacher, Simon Sechter,
in harmony and counterpoint.
In fact, he worked so hard that
his teacher was impelled to write
him a letter which said,
"I do implore you to take care of
yourself and allow yourself
sufficient relaxation."
# Locus iste
# A Deo factus est... #
If anything,
Bruckner's love for the church was
becoming even more intense.
This motet, written for the
dedication of a chapel in Linz,
seems to translate this love
directly into music.
Locus iste a Deo factus est,
inaestimabile sacramentum
irreprehensibilis est.
This dwelling is God's handiwork,
a mystery beyond price
that cannot be spoken against.
# Inaestimabile sacramentum
# Inaestimabile sacramentum... #
His Catholicism speaks through maybe
in the simplicity of what he does
but also in the waves of
sounds and emotion.
Even something as simple as Locus
Iste, starts so quietly, so gently
but it goes through
this massive sound in the middle.
It really feels like opening a
door into his religious landscape.
# Irreprehensibilis est... #
After 10 years in Linz,
Bruckner, aged 42,
suffered a severe nervous breakdown
and was sent to a sanatorium.
# ..A Deo factus est... #
He described it as a condition of
utter degradation and loneliness.
It drove him to the edge of suicide.
Although he recovered, this time,
it left a legacy of anxiety
and fear and he decided
he had to leave Linz.
For the rest of his long life,
he earned his living as a teacher
of music while struggling
to build his reputation as a
symphonic composer in the capital
of the Austrian Empire, Vienna.
The apartment that was Bruckner's
home for nigh on two decades is now
a suite in the Hotel de France.
Guten Abend.
By the 1870s, both Brahms and
Bruckner had made their homes
here in the Austrian capital.
Brahms, now a musical celebrity
thanks to the German Requiem,
was in his mid-30.
Bruckner, around 10 years older,
was still working in semi-obscurity.
So, I'll be sleeping tonight
in Anton Bruckner's room.
It feels slightly odd, when we've
lost so much of the physical world
that these two composers knew,
to be here,
somewhere quite so intimate.
I don't expect to
see any ghosts but...
I do expect a good night's sleep.
MUSIC: Symphony No. 4, 3rd movement
by Bruckner
For both composers,
Vienna was the ultimate test.
It could lay claim to be the
European capital of music,
indeed of the arts.
And any German-speaking composer
must have dreamt of making it here.
Brahms rented two rooms
here in Karlsgasse.
A friend described them as a sort
of place suitable for a student,
a minor civil servant,
or a salesman starting out in trade.
They were, frankly, shabby.
And in Viennese eyes, at least,
not remotely appropriate
for a great artist.
But then, that was typical
of the man. He was a bundle
of contradictions -
mean-spirited, yet tender.
Progressive, reactionary.
He once boasted that he could find
any passage in his Bible instantly,
even in the dark.
Like Bruckner,
he was still writing sacred music.
Above all, he was drawn to the bleak
agony and the harsh questions
of the Book of Job.
# Warum
# Warum ist das Licht... #
"Wherefore is light given to him
that is in misery,
"and life unto the bitter in soul,
which long for death
but it cometh not?
"Why is light given
to a man whose way is hid
"and whom God hath hedged in?"
If A German Requiem had
promised comfort
to the living in the presence of
death,
then this motet, with its cry of
despair and subsequent sense of
stoic resignation,
offers another
individual response to the deaths
that had clouded Brahms' life.
It was inevitable
that Brahms and Bruckner would meet.
But surprisingly, it was neither
in the concert hall, nor the church.
Our two composers had a taste
for cold draught Pilsner.
And the best beer in Vienna could
be found at an eating house called
Zum Roten Igel, the Red Hedgehog.
The place range with
the sounds of fierce arguments
between various cliques
proselytising for their
chosen musical champions.
Accounts of the two masters
meeting bristled with discomfort
and suppressed aggression.
Brahms privately thought Bruckner
a deluded fool, ruined by priests,
his music was a swindle.
Bruckner, meanwhile,
dismissed Brahms as a craftsman,
not a composer.
Danke schon. In the best description
we have of one of their encounters,
Brahms is cold and dismissive,
whilst Bruckner, always polite,
sometimes even obsequious, scuttles
off to get his great rival a beer.
Nice and cold.
# Ecce sacerdos magnus
# Ecce sacerdos
# Magnus. #
This is Bruckner's rather
bird-like face with, in this case,
quite a beady stare.
He never sported a beard,
unlike more fashionable men
of his time,
and he was mocked by
the sophisticated Viennese
for his odd behaviour.
And is there an indication
here too, in his expression,
of the insecurities he often
felt about the wider world
beyond the safety of the Church?
Bruckner's writing is so of him
and his beliefs.
You see that same
fervour and personality
and love of his church
coming through.
His sheer power, emotion,
is so profound.
He has put so much of his own
personality into the music.
VOICES GRADUALLY RISE
IN A LOUD CRESCENDO
It's loud, isn't it?
It is very loud.
It's the impact,
the cumulative impact. Fantastic.
Can you tell me how Bruckner
achieves his effects in this?
In this particular piece,
he uses a sort of refrain, really,
he uses it three times in all.
And he builds it up from a succession
of root position chords. The simplest
chords you can get. Absolutely, yes.
He starts in E major, then goes
to A minor, right through, G major,
E flat, ending up in C major.
He goes right through
the progression. We're going to sing
that progression of chords.
THEY SING THROUGH
THE CHORD PROGRESSION
That's fantastic, and they don't
quite go where you'd expect them to.
There are a couple
of surprises in there.
And at the beginning, he just has the
sopranos and altos with the organ,
and the men are with the trombones,
until we get to this fantastic
F major, C major finish.
Everything comes together,
it's quite brilliant. Let's hear it.
THEY SING, REPEATING
THE SECTION IN FULL
The power and originality
of Bruckner's sacred music
proved to be no barrier
to its ready acceptance as music
for worship in the Catholic Church.
But for his secular orchestral
music, it was a different story.
The musical establishment's
response to his earliest symphonies
was criticism and indifference.
Then, after 20 years of
misunderstanding, his 7th Symphony,
as vast and ambitious as a
cathedral, found an audience.
But the recognition Anton Bruckner
craved had come almost too late.
As he grew older,
he was unable to hide his
increasingly obsessive behaviour.
What started out simply
as counting bars in music,
erupted into numeromania.
He would count everything,
grains of sand, stars in the sky,
leaves on a tree, even the pearls
set on to ladies' dresses,
rigorously returning to his starting
point when he lost his tally.
And his prayers, always strictly
observed, became ever more feverish.
For Bruckner, every experience was
intense and absolute, and every act
of composition was an act of prayer.
In the Roman Catholic faith, the
Virgin Mary is a bringer of comfort.
And in his profound devotion to her,
Bruckner set the text, Ave Maria,
three times.
# Benedicta tu in mulieribus
# Et benedictus
# Fructus ventris tui. #
In his final year,
Bruckner, now frail and with
a mind wandering alarmingly,
was offered a place to
live by the Emperor himself,
here at the Belvedere Palace.
He must have felt extremely proud
that a man from a small village
in Upper Austria
had been deemed worthy
of such an honour.
# Jesus...! #
His last day start unexceptionally.
He worked in the morning on
the finale of his 9th Symphony,
then in the early afternoon, he went
for a stroll in the public gardens.
He then returned to his small
apartment where he died.
The funeral of Anton Bruckner
took place on 4th October 1896
in Vienna's most beautiful church,
the Karlskirche.
The church was packed.
When Brahms came
to pay his respects,
an attendant assured him that, yes,
they could probably squeeze him in.
But he hesitated,
and then turned to leave.
He was heard to mutter,
"Never mind, soon my coffin."
Bruchner's body was brought home
to the monastery of St Florian,
and laid to rest directly underneath
the great organ on which he had
learned to play and to compose.
Once, when he was asked what
he might say to his God
if required to give an account
of his life here on Earth,
Bruckner allegedly replied,
"I will present to him the score
of some of my work,
"and he will judge me mercifully."
# Amen. #
Johannes Brahms was only
63 when Bruckner died,
but his life too was nearly over.
If Bruckner was assured
of the immortality of his soul,
then Brahms was assured
of this - that his immortality
lay in his work.
# Mit Fried und Freud
# Ich fahr dahin
# In Gottes
# Willen
# Getrost ist mir
# Mein Herz
# Und Sinn. #
He composed less and less
during those final years,
and inevitably friends
that he had cared for and
members of his family died.
He must have been hit terribly
hard in 1896 when he heard of
the death of Clara Schumann.
She had been his greatest friend
ever since that first meeting
in Dusseldorf 40 years earlier.
Now, the last link with
Brahms's inspiration and hero,
Robert Schumann, was gone.
His last composition was
this set of organ preludes
based on chorales that he must
have heard in church as a child.
There were found at his
apartment after his death.
Perhaps he would never
have published them himself.
Simple and sweetly melancholic,
they seem to look back to the
happier days of Brahms's youth.
It's kind of difficult to work out
exactly what he was hoping to achieve
with these chorale preludes,
but I think that it was just a sort
of homage to Robert Schumann and
Clara, and it's the sort of thing
that people do in later life,
which is to go back to something
that they feel has been left undone.
That may well have been it.
It took a long time for Brahms
to admit he was ill with cancer.
But, inevitably, the time came
when he had to take to his bed,
and finally, on 3rd April 1897,
Johannes Brahms died.
This is where Brahms
was finally laid to rest.
In what he himself
had called a sacred place.
Next to his friend Johann Strauss,
and near Schubert and Beethoven.
A great composer amongst his peers.
MUSIC: Requiem, Op. 48,
Johannes Brahms
For Brahms, life was a struggle,
something to be endured.
His music doesn't seem to have been
written in praise of God, nor does
he really address him directly.
The nearest he comes to that
is to ask the question, why?
And even then,
he seems uncertain as to whether
God is actually listening.
His music provides us, his fellow
human beings, with comfort,
glimpses of a transient beauty,
and perhaps the promise after
death of a long sought-for
and well-deserved rest.
In the next episode of Sacred Music,
my journey takes me to Paris
to discover the exquisitely French
church music of Gabriel Faure
and Francis Poulenc.
Subtitles by Red Bee Media Ltd
E-mail subtitling@bbc.co.uk